Finding Aid for David Emil Heineman papers, 1899-1912
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
David Emil Heineman papers 1899-1912
Heineman, David Emil, 1865-1935.
18 volumes (in 3 boxes) and 1 oversize folder
851460 Aa 2; Ac
Detroit, Michigan, merchant and attorney, state legislator from Wayne County, Michigan, later Detroit city councilman; scrapbooks, photographs, and miscellanea.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of Mrs. John T. Norton (donor no. 2284 ) and came to the library in 1947.
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
David Emil Heineman was born in Detroit on Oct. 17, 1865. He graduated from Detroit High School in 1883 and from the University of Michigan in 1887. He studied for a year in the law school of the University, then in the law offices of E. C. Walker, C. I. Walker and C. A. Kent of Detroit. He was admitted to the bar in 1889. In 1893, he was appointed chief assistant city attorney of Detroit. After three years, he returned to private practice. From 1899 to 1900, he served in the state legislature for the First District of Wayne County. Besides his law practice Heineman served on the Detroit City Council and was active in Detroit cultural and philanthropic organizations. He died in 1935.
The collection is comprised mainly of eighteen scrapbooks containing newspaper clippings with some photographs documenting both the political career of Heineman and the politics of Detroit, in general in the period of the first decade of the twentieth century. There is also a photograph album of the Heineman home, and memorial clippings following his death.
Subjects:
Detroit (Mich.); Michigan--Politics and government--1899-1916.; Municipal government--Michigan--Detroit.; Michigan--Politics and government--1837-1950.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Detroit (Mich.)--Dwellings.; Dwellings--Michigan--Detroit.; Heineman, David Emil, 1865-1935.; Interiors--1910.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Scrapbooks, 1899-1912
  - 1899-1900 (Box 1)
  - 1901-1903 (Box 1)
  - 1903 (Box 1)
  - 1903-1904 (Box 1)
  - 1904 (Box 1)
  - 1904-1905 (Box 1)
  - 1905 (Box 2)
  - 1905-1906 (Box 2)
  - 1906 (Box 2)
  - 1906-1907 (Box 2)
  - 1907 (Box 2)
  - 1907-1908 (Box 2)
  - 1908 (Box 3)
  - 1908-1909 (Box 3)
  - 1909-1910 (Box 3)
  - 1910-1912 (Box 3)
- Other materials
  - Memorial upon his death in 1935 (Box 3)
  - Photograph Album, 1910 of the Heineman home (Box 3)
  - Portrait (Box 3)
  - Poem written by Isidore Frankel and dedicated to Emil Heineman (Folder 1)